Hello, this is Martin
Gerdes. This lecture
is on histology of
vessels and lymphatics.
These are the session
objectives that you
should be able to
compare and contrast
large, medium, small
arteries and veins.
You should be able to
describe the difference
between capillary
types and how their
morphology varies according
to their function.
Discuss the histology
and functional lymphatic
vessels, the unique functions
of endothelial cells, and
microvascular components
that regulate blood flow.
These are the general
concepts. Arteries
and veins have three
layers, the tunica
intima, tunica media,
and tunica adventitia.
The innermost layer of
endothelium has a basal lamina
associated with
endothelial cells,
and then there's also
a sub-endothelial
layer of loose
connective tissue.
Arteries have a sub
-endothelial layer of intima
that contains a sheet
-like layer of lamellae of
fenestrated elastic material.
This is the internal
elastic membrane, which,
like substances, diffuse
through and reach cells
deep in the vessel wall.
The tunica media,
the middle layer,
is mainly circumferentially
arranged layers
of smooth muscle cells.
In arteries, this
layer is very thick
and extends from the
internal to the external
elastic membrane.
The latter is a
layer of elastin that
separates the tunica
media from the tunica
adventitia. The outer
layer of tunica adventitia
is primarily a
connective tissue layer.
It contains other things,
among other things,
a vasovasorum and the
blood supply, which
is the blood supply
to vessel walls. This
is particularly true
in the larger vessels.
So here's a cartoon
giving you the
general features
of blood vessels.
And one thing you will
learn is that it's
best to compare
vessels of a similar
size, in other words,
matching vessels.
Sometimes it's difficult
to completely characterize
a particular blood
vessel independently
because there is some
variation to the theme.
But primarily, and
here you can see,
the tunica intima
is in dark gray,
the tunica media
is in blue, and
the adventitia
is in light gray.
So if you compare the aorta
and the inferior vena cava,
you can see right away
the prominent layer in
the aorta is the tunica
media, which in the case
of the aorta also has a
lot of elastic components
because the aorta is a
highly elastic vessel.
And you can see the tunica
intima is also
fairly prominent.
The tunica adventitia,
not so prominent in
the aorta. The comparable
vessel, the vena
cava, is pretty much
dominated by the tunica
adventitia in the outer
layer, which also has
longitudinally running
smooth muscle cells.
muscular arteries you can
see here have a prominent
tunica media and the veins
have a prominent tunica
adventitia arterioles
you can see here and
venules you can see here so
the main difference is in
arteries the tunica media
is more prominent in
veins the tunica adventitia
is more prominent here
you can see an elastic
stain of aorta you can see
all the which sustains
black you can see that the
tunica media in aorta is
really loaded with elastic
components the adventitia
is out here so here is a
histology slide of aorta
and if you look at the vena
cava you can see there's a
tunica intima which is lined
by simple squamous endothelial
cells the the other
layers are a little bit
more difficult to define in
this case these cells here
are running circumferentially
and would be considered
part of the tunica media,
whereas tunica adventitia
probably starts right about
here and is comprised of
mostly of connective tissue,
but also some longitudinally
oriented smooth muscle
cells. So again, a major
feature is that the boundaries
of the three layers are
not very clear on the
venous side as compared to
the arterial side here is
a muscular artery and you
can see this elastin stain
stains the internal elastic
lamina and you can make
out a little bit of the
external elastic lamina again
the prominent layer here is
the tunica media and also
you can still see a fairly
prominent and ventitia.
And here's an example of
a matching vein. Now, this
internal layer is actually
clotted blood cells. You
can see occasional white
blood cell nucleus here, but
this is red blood cells
and white blood cells that
are clotted. As you remember
from your cadavers after
death the a large part of
the blood pools and the
venous side and you can see
that spread so so this is
actually the the internal
surface of the vein here so
this would be simple squamous
endothelial cells and
you can see here some smooth
muscle cells here so this
would probably be the
boundary of the tunica media
and the tunica
adventitia is here on the
outside as far as
arterioles go you can see
simple squamous endothelium
and a layer of about one
to three smooth muscle cells
and some external connective
tissue also but not very
much the the venule on
the other end is primarily
just it's a little bit larger
if you look at matched
arteriole and venule the
venule tends to have a little
bit larger diameter and
And also is prominent in
simple squamous endothelium.
Not very much of any
smooth muscle cells,
but some connective
tissue on the outside.
So again, when comparing
vessels, it's good to look
at paired vessels. Arteries
have a thicker wall
and a relatively thicker
tunica media. Veins have
thinner walls, larger and
more collapsed lumen, and
the tunica adventitia is
relatively more prominent.
And another thing
that you also see,
oftentimes you see blood
cells from the vascular
supply, which would
be red blood cells
and white blood cells
that are in the veins post
-mortem, but generally
not in the arteries.
So here is a cartoon that
pretty much gives you
an overview of the
structure of arteries and
veins and also the capillary
network in between.
So as you can see here,
the prominent layer of
the artery is the middle
layer, the tunica media.
and the prominent layer
of the venous side is
primarily the tunic
adventitia, the outer layer.
Here you can see an example of
an artery and a matching vein.
Again, you notice
the vein is much
more collapsed and
larger in diameter.
It does have some smooth
muscle cells, but not
nearly as prominent as the
tunic media of the artery.
Artery is a large artery,
is an elastic artery,
have a diameter of greater
than one centimeter.
So think garden hose
here, about that size.
Medium artery is a
muscular artery and
of two to ten
millimeters in diameter.
Small arteries are from
about 0.1 to 2 millimeters.
arterioles are anywhere
between 5 and 30 microns
and have smooth muscle
layer 1 to 2 or 3 cells.
Capillaries range in
size throughout the
body but are approximately
4 to 10 microns
and they're pretty
much only endothelium.
Veins, you have post capillary
venial which is about
10 to 50 microns in diameter
they have only endothelium
but also have some parasites
which are cells that we'll
talk about later a muscular
venue that would would
be a little bit larger venue
and these are between 1500
microns in diameter they
have a smooth muscle cell
layer one to two cells a
small vein is about point one
to one millimeter a medium
vein is about one to ten
millimeters a large vein again
larger than one centimeter
i don't expect you to know
all of these numbers but
you should have a pretty
good general idea of the size
range of the different
subclasses of veins and venules
and also of arteries
and arterioles
so large elastic arteries
have again simple
squamous endothelium
connective tissue and elastin
and the subendothelium
and they have internal
elastic lamina which are
these fenestrated sheets
the tunica media has smooth
muscle spindle shaped cells
of course the smooth muscle
cells collagen and ground
muscle ground substance
made from smooth muscle
cells not fiberglass that's
an interesting point here is
that in the large elastic
arteries you have secretions
from the smooth muscle
cells that are actually
collagenous in nature the tunica
adventitia there is separated
by an external elastic
lamina from the tunica media
and there's collagen fibers
elastic fibers but not
sheets in the adventitia
fibroblasts and macrophages
also in the larger vessels
like like elastic arteries
you can have basa vasorum
and nerve vascularis these
are nerves that actually
enter the tunic adventitia of
these large elastic arteries
now in large elastic
arteries like the aorta it's
difficult to determine the
internal and external elastic
lamina because what you
have is continuous sheets of
fenestrated elastic lamina
from the internal elastic
lamina all the way through
the media so pretty much
it's the innermost elastic
sheet and the outermost
elastic sheet that
should be the internal
elastic internal and
external elastic lamina
in elastic arteries.
So here's a histological
slide. You can see
the tunica intima here
with endothelial lining.
And here you can see
the tunica media.
And there are some elastin
sheets here. You can see
right here, this line here.
These are elastic sheets.
Some more here. in between
smooth muscle cells.
So large elastic arteries,
examples are the aorta and
pulmonary artery. They
conduct blood from the heart.
Pressure generated by
ventricular contractions.
The systole moves the
blood through the elastic
arteries and causes the wall
of the large elastic arteries
to distend. So during
diastole, there is some
recoil because of the
elastic fibers in the wall of
these vessels that tends to
distend with contraction.
And there's this recoil
during diastole that helps to
maintain the pressure a
little bit higher. Otherwise,
you would have a, if these
were not this elastic,
you would have a really
dramatic drop from the systolic
to the diastolic blood
pressure, which would probably
be a little bit harder for
the cells and tissue to
handle on a beat-by-beat
basis. So this is an important
adaptation, adding elasticity
to these large arteries.
So again, this is what
I just identified,
endothelial lining
with basal lamina.
The long axis of the
endothelial cells runs
parallel with the
direction of blood flow.
these endothelial cells
are joined with tight
junctions and also gap
junctions subendothelial layer
connective tissue has an
internal elastic lamina
muscular arteries these
are pretty much the
named arteries like
the internal thoracic
artery for instance
or the right coronary
artery so these are
the muscular arteries
And you have an endotunica
intima that's composed of
endothelium, subendothelium,
which is fairly sparse,
not a very prominent layer
of the tunica intima.
But the internal
elastic lamina in the
large muscular
arteries is prominent.
In the tunica media, this
is the thickest layer
of muscular arteries, and
the smooth muscle layer
is really very dramatic
in muscular arteries.
collagen a little bit of
elastin and of course the
external elastic lamina
is pretty distinct in
the large muscular arteries
but as you get smaller
and smaller the arteries
the external elastic
lamina tends to disappear
first and then later the
internal elastic lamina
becomes less conspicuous.
Tunica adventitia has
collagen fibers, elastic
fibers, fibroblasts,
some adipose, and the
larger vessels, vasovasorum
and nervi vascularis,
nerves and blood supply
to the blood supply.
So here's an example of
a muscular artery, and
what you notice This is
a very thick layer of
tunica media which is
smooth muscle cells,
mostly circumferentially.
You can see the nuclei
are more elongated here
which indicates that
the muscle cells are
running circumferentially.
And the tunica intima is
very small but you can see
these internal elastic
lamina just under there maybe
a little bit more obvious
over here so this is internal
elastic lamina so the the
tunica intima would be
very small pretty much just
a layer of endothelium and
a very small amount of
connective tissue the tunica
adventitia begins right here
so this is all the tunica
adventitia yeah again and
the larger arteries here
you can see here you can see
elastic membrane here but
the external elastic lamina
is not quite so obvious
on this vessel if you had
a little bit larger vessel
it would become more
prominent as you move down to
smaller and smaller arteries
the external elastic lamina
begins to disappear and
you still see the internal
elastic lamina until you get
to the very small arteries
so again here is small
arteries to the arterioles
the tunic intima as the
endothelium internal elastic
lamina, but only in the
larger ones. Smooth muscle is
about eight layers in
the small artery, but in
arterioles, only about one to
two layers of smooth muscle.
Some collagen in the largest
of the small arteries.
Connective tissue, there's a
little bit of
connective tissue.
Arterioles regulate blood
flow to capillaries. So one
thing you should really
understand, the arterioles
are really important because
they not only regulate
blood flow they also regulate
blood pressure so in other
words if you have all these
arterioles peripherally
dilate at the same time you
would have a sudden drop
in blood pressure systolic
diastolic blood pressure
And there are also
some specialized
arterioles that
act as AV shunts.
So arterial regulation,
precapillary sphincters,
or slight thickening
of smooth muscle cells
at the origin of the
capillary bed from an
arteriole, we'll show a
picture of that next slide.
Arterials can dilate
up to 100% from
resting diameter and
can maintain up to a
40% constriction for
a very long time.
Large decrease or increase
in vascular resistance
has a direct effect on
blood flow and systemic
arterial pressure, as
I indicated earlier.
This helps to, as these
arterioles dilate and contract,
this regulates blood flow
to different regions.
For instance, during exercise,
blood flow to skeletal
muscle is increased by
dilatation of arterioles,
providing the skeletal
muscle, while blood flow
to the intestine is
reduced by arterial or
constriction so with exercise
blood flow is diverted from
the GI tract to the
skeletal muscle of the body
capillaries allow fluid
containing gases metabolites
waste products to diffuse
through the thin wall
there are single layer of
endothelial cells simple
squamous epithelium and
there they have basal
lamina. There's three types,
continuous, fenestrated,
and discontinuous, which
we will talk about now.
So the three basic types,
now again, tunica enema
of capillaries is pretty
much the whole game,
one to three endothelial
cells, and then a basal
lamina or basement
membrane on the outside.
So there is no tunica media or
tunica adventitia
in capillaries.
So the continuous
capillaries are the major
capillaries in the body and
they metabolites in oxygen,
tissue waste, carbon
dioxide can pass through the
wall of these continuous
capillaries. So they are
found in muscle, lungs,
central nervous system.
They may have parasites,
particularly as you get towards
the end of the capillary,
towards the venous side.
Fenestrated capillaries,
this is an example of
fenestrated capillary over
here, and you can see that they
have pores. You can see
these little dots here have
pores, and these diaphragms
are these pores. I'll talk
about that and show a better
example of that later.
But the fenestrated
capillaries are found,
they're pretty much good for
absorption and filtration
and secretion. So
they're found in the
intestine, the kidneys,
and the endocrine system.
So these allow passage of
larger particles than a
continuous, because of
these pores with diaphragms.
Discontinuous capillaries,
these are in sinuses,
and you can see here,
you can see there's
the endothelial cells
have openings. They are
not continuous, and
the basal lamina is not
continuous either. So these
are present as sinusoids,
like the liver, spleen,
and bone marrow.
So here is an example of a
continuous capillary here.
And you can see here's
a boundary between one
of the endothelial
cells. So these are tight
junctions. So, you can
have diffusion of gaseous
things and some other
molecules, but these capillaries
are more of a boundary
than the other types
of capillaries, like
fenestrated capillaries.
this is an example of a
fenestrated capillary here
you can see they also
have a basal lamina but
you see these fenestrations
and this is shown
better at a higher
magnification here in the
right so you can see the
basement membrane here
You can also see the
endothelial cell here, and
there is a pore right
here with a diaphragm.
So endothelial cells do
a lot. They're not just a
static tube liner. They
maintain a permeability barrier
to simple diffusion, active
transport, penocytosis,
receptor-mediated endocytosis.
So, they are really
important in determining
what goes into and
what leaves the tissue.
They also have a non
-thrombogenic barrier.
They provide a non-thrombogenic
barrier. Now, I don't
expect you to know all of
these players down here, but
I'd like to introduce
them here. Other lectures,
subsequent lectures are going
to go into these in more
detail. but the endothelial
cells have antithrombogenic
agents and they also have
some prothrombogenic agents.
They're important in
regulating clotting and
preventing clotting of
these blood vessels or
allowing clotting when
there's a traumatic
injury to a blood
vessel and the clotting
process is important in
stopping the blood flow.
So the endothelial
cells play a major role
in these substances.
Now, you're going to
learn a lot more about
all of these later on.
And I will not really quiz
you on my test questions,
but be aware of the
basic function of the
endothelial cells forming
a non-thrombogenic barrier.
all the players you will
learn about later. They
modulate blood flow and
vascular resistance. So
endothelial cells, they
secrete vasoconstrictors and
vasodilators, particularly
like nitrous oxide is an
important vasodilator that
you may have heard of.
They also regulate cell growth.
For So, they can actually
secrete these growth
factors that trigger
growth of themselves.
And they're also involved
in the immune response,
exorcellular matrix, and
lipoprotein metabolism.
And you'll get into
a lot more of these
functions later on
in other lectures.
Arteriovanous shunts are
fairly common in the body.
they can become pathological.
So these arteriovenous
shunts allows
blood to bypass the capillaries
and go directly from the
arteries to the veins.
An AV fistula is an
abnormal connection that
can lead to volume
overloading of the heart.
Say, for instance, if you
had a stab wound to the
abdomen, it could pierce
the wall of the aorta
and the vena cava and
this would allow arterial
blood to to because there
is a sheath around that
often contained it will
allow arterial blood
to go directly from the
artery to the vein and
vena cava and this would
bypass the capillary bed
So this would be a
pathological situation, and if
the shunt is really
big, it can cause heart
enlargement, severe heart
enlargement in some cases.
There are normal AV
shunts, and some of
these AV shunts are
preferential through
-fares. I'll show
an example of that.
And the proximal segment
is known as a metarterial.
and they allow some
blood to pass more
directly from the artery
to the vein so this is
a normal AV shot and
there's a lack of a pre
-capillary sphincter at
the venous end of this
so there the blood can
bypass the capillaries.
These are commonly found in
the fingertips, the nose,
lips, erectile tissue of
the ***** and the ********.
They serve in thermal
regulation of body surface area.
For instance, if you close
an AV shunt in the skin,
this causes blood to flow
through the capillary bed,
and this enhances heat
loss. And then if those are
constricted, then the blood in
the skin would flow directly
through this AV shunt and
would not warm the skin.
So, here's the normal
AV shunting mechanism,
and here you can see
there is a metarterial
here where blood can
flow directly through
without any sphincters
impeding its flow.
But if these precapillary
sphincters are open
here, all along here,
then you have blood
flowing through the
capillary bed and back to
the venous side so here
you can see with the
these sphincters are
closed you have blood
flowing straight through
this av shunt or this
thoroughfare channel
postcapillary venules
and small veins
again tunic enema
is endothelium
postcapillary venules
and lymph nodes have some
unusual specialization,
which you'll learn
about later in the
lymphatic system. They have
these high endothelial
cells that are more of a
cuboidal shape than a
squamous endothelial. So
there are some modifications
in the body to the
tunica intima of
postcapillary venules.
Tunica media is one or two
layers of smooth muscle in
small veins. There's no
tunica media present in
postcapillary venules. You do
have parasites in postcapillary
venules, and we'll talk
more about them later.
Tunica advent tissue,
advent tissue of connective
tissue. It's a thin
layer in small veins, but
not really apparent in
post capillary venules.
So these vessels
respond to histamine,
which increases the
capillary permeability, and
serotonin, which mostly
leads to contraction.
You'll learn more
about that later when
you get into the
regulation of blood flow.
So, pericytes are really
interesting cells.
We have not really
understood them
very well until more recently.
Pericytes are a common
feature in post capillary
venules and some continuous
capillaries, particularly
towards the end as you
get to the venous side.
they're surrounded they
surround the venule
or capillary with branching
cytoplasmic process
they're enclosed by
basal lamina which is
continuous with that of
the endothelial cells
and they're derived from
the same precursor cells
that form endothelial cells
so they're closely related
pericytes give rise to
endothelial and smooth
muscle cells during
vessel growth so
they're actually actively
involved in wound
healing and they can
have some contractility
and respond to nitrous oxide
so here is a schematic of
a pericyte you can see this
is like a capillary here
with a basement membrane and
this would be the pericyte
here you can see they have
these processes that wrap
around the vessel and I have
electron micrograph that
I've done of the heart and
you can see there's a
pericyte here another pericyte
here this is scanning electron
micrograph you can see
heart muscle cells here
and these are blood vessels
throughout the heart that are
still present after we digested
the surface so we could
better see these vessels.
And here's another
example of a parasite from
an electron micrograph
I did of Radhart.
You can see the Radhart
muscle here and here,
capillary here, and this is
a pericyte nucleus present
on the outer surface here.
If you zoomed in here,
you can see the basal lamina
going around the end of
the parasite, continuous
with the basal lamina of the
capillary medium-sized
veins are again like the
medium-sized arteries or
the named veins in the body
they have valves
characteristically especially in
the legs where gravity
is as an important force
for veins because they're
they're not high pressure
they're low pressure and
they're trying to return
blood if If you're an
erect mammal like we are,
the blood is going
back in a low-pressure
situation but against
the force of gravity.
So as a result of
this, we have veins
and we have valves
in the larger veins.
So it's a tunica enema, it's an
endothelium, and the
subendothelium, it's
thin with occasional
smooth muscle.
There are some smooth
muscle cells in the media,
but much thinner than
a medium-sized artery.
Again, it would be
much easier to identify
a matched pair of a
vein and an artery.
So you can do a relative
comparison because
there are some differences
in isolation, particularly
if you look at veins
in isolation that
come from the lower
extremity where gravity is
important compared to
the upper extremity where
gravity is not very
important, like the head.
So because of
these differences,
regional differences, a
similar size medium vein
might look quite different
from the lower extremity
compared to the upper
extremity. So again, Again,
we would not expect you
to identify the difference
between arteries and
veins, except when you have
like a match pair, so you
can compare them directly.
Tutica adventitious, thickest
layer in medium veins.
It has elastic fibers,
collagen, smooth muscle.
So again, here's a medium
vein. Again, this is coagulated
blood on the internal
surface. You can see that
these are mostly red blood
cells, but you can see occasional
white blood cell. This
is not one of the layers.
This is the inner layer
here, the tunica intima.
And the boundary is not
really clear, but this would
be here. You can see
smooth muscle cells going
circumferentially. So this would
be part of the tunica media.
and then the adventitia
would be right here mostly
connective tissue with
some fibroblasts occasional
spood muscle cell large
veins so large veins have an
endothelium a thin subendothelium
which is a boundary
between the tunica intima
and media is not often
very clear tunica media is
relatively thin with mostly
circular smooth muscle, some
fibroblasts and collagen.
Again, this would be
a much less pronounced
tunica media than you have
in a matching large artery.
Tunica adventitia is the
main layer of a large vein.
Like we're talking about
subclavian veins or vana
cava for instance there's
longitudinal smooth muscle
also in the adventitia
fibroblasts collagen
elastic fibers so the smooth
muscle in the large veins
is important as you will
learn physiologically
because the large veins
are largely a reservoir of
blood so that if you have a
sudden need for an increase
in cardiac output, like
you're running away from
the tiger and your heart
starts to beat faster,
the smooth muscle in
these large veins can
contract and provide a
sudden burst of blood to
the heart to help increase
the cardiac output.
Again, as I've indicated,
gravity can affect
the structure,
particularly of the veins.
I point out the large veins in
the head have thinner walls.
The saphenous vein
in the legs is so
muscular that it
is a preferred vein
to use for coronary
bypass surgery.
Because it already
has a relatively
thick muscular wall for a vein.
And of course veins
can be removed
much more readily
than arteries.
so they're a preferred method
for doing bypass surgery.
So here's a large vein.
Again, here's the
tunica intima here.
You can barely make out
the boundary, but here's
smooth muscle cells are
running circumferentially,
so this would be part
of the tunica media.
probably again the the
boundary is not clear probably
this layer would be considered
the tunica media and
here would be the tunica
adventitia what you notice here
in this cross-section large
vein is that these smooth
muscle cells are cut in
cross sections so they're
running towards you
longitudinally whereas the smooth
muscle cells of the media are
running circumferentially.
Again the smooth muscle
is not very prominent
in veins, much more
prominent in arteries.
Example of an arterial,
venial, small lymphatic
vessel. Here you can see
an arterial here with
about two layers of
smooth muscle. You can
see endothelial nuclei
poking out in the lumen.
One thing that you'll
notice about arterioles,
they tend to have a
fairly thick wall compared
to their size. So arterioles
tend to have a nice
round lumen, whereas the
matching venule is mostly
endothelium. It's much
more dilated and you
tend to have blood
accumulated post-mortem so you
can see red blood cells
and white blood cells
there is some connective
tissue around that but
these are not clear
layers as you would find
in the larger veins this is
probably a lymphatic vessel
here you can see it's kind
of matched with the artery
and the vein but it has
even it's even much more
dilated than the vein but it
doesn't have any cells within
the lumen. That would be
typical. Now, in some cases,
you might see only white
blood cells in a lymphatic
vessel. That would be a
key identifier that it is a
lymphatic vessel if it has
only white blood cells, which
happens after the lymphatics
pass through the lymph
nodes they tend to accumulate
more white blood cells so
a key feature as i
mentioned before are
valves on the inside
of the large veins so
you can read this
later but let me give
an overview of this
i think you will find
this to be a very
important clinical alert
historically and you should
pay attention to this i
think because this is a
this is a development and
particularly in cardiology
that's going to seriously impact
patient treatment and
outcome we traditionally have
divided heart disease into
ischemic and non-ischemic
so by ischemic we mean
obstructed coronary arteries.
So there are, typically
there's progressive narrowing
of coronary arteries where
you finally get to 90%
occlusion. That's when you
start showing symptoms at rest.
But we look at other types
of heart disease where
you have patent coronary
arteries where there's not
any obvious reduction in
the lumen of the major
coronary arteries. This
has been traditionally
characterized as non-ischemic
heart disease, but what
we have found more recently
is in the non-ischemic
heart disease, and again,
this is an explosion of
the literature in recent
years that's showing that
just about every type of
heart disease, whether
it's dilated or non-dilated
heart failure, diabetic
cardiomyopathy, All of
these have, there's been
many reports of impaired
microvascular blood flow.
So what this means is
non-ischemic patients,
you know, probably
are actually ischemic,
but at the microvascular
level. In other
words, they have patent
coronary arteries.
This has been underreported
traditionally because
to measure microvascular
blood flow, PET scan
has been the traditional
method, and that requires
a radioisotope, and
we're adverse to giving
patients radioisotopes
unless completely necessary.
And again, previously,
these patients
were identified as
ischemic and non-ischemic
based on the coronary
arteries alone.
Now, the newer non-radioactive
technology is rapidly
moving forward, and this is
a reason why there's more
reports of microvascular
blood flow impairment in heart
disease and in fact just
about everywhere we've looked
there's impaired microvascular
blood flow you should
be aware that research has
been done right here at
nyitcom primarily in my lab
and my collaborator kayo yama
we have basically
found in all of our
animal models even if
the serum levels of t3
are normal, there are
below normal tissue
levels of T3 in the
heart muscle itself.
And T3 is an
important regulator
of microvascular blood flow.
We have, for instance,
found in an animal model of
diabetic cardiomyopathy, a
paper published from here a
few years ago, that in
animals, the rats that were
treated with T3 as we induced
diabetic cardiomyopathy,
they had no indication of
heart disease. They still
had diabetes, but it completely
prevented their heart
disease, and it prevented
the remodeling of the most
important vessels that
regulate microvascular blood
flow, the arterioles. I'm
pretty sure we're going to
find this to be true in
patients, so this is something
I think you should pay
attention to going forward.
And there's an overwhelming
amount of information,
many, many studies that
have been published right
here from NYTCOM that
suggests that there is a very
extensive amount of low
tissue T3 levels in heart
disease. There's not any
current data available for
human hearts that with
a mass spec T3 analysis,
we've established that
technique now with Cold Spring
Harbor Labs. So hopefully
we'll provide that data
in the very near future,
and we'll be able to confirm
what we've found in
animals, that human hearts
and heart disease actually
have low T3 levels too.
Again, this is an area
that you should pay
attention to because the
more and more we look in
clinical studies at
microvascular blood flow
impairment, the more we
find. Our studies here even
show that in rats with a
heart attack, in the non
-infarcted area of the
heart, there appears to be
evidence of impaired
microvascular blood flow.
So, lymphatics, we're
not going to talk, we're
mainly going to just talk
about lymphatic vessels.
With that, we're not
going to talk about
some of the major
organs involved in the
lymphatic system, like
the appendix, or the
thymus, or the spleen,
or the pyrus patches.
We're mainly going to talk
about the vessels themselves.
So, lymphatic vessels,
they are unidirectional.
They can convey fluid
only from tissues, not to
tissues. The smallest are
lymphatic capillaries.
There are numerous and
loose connective tissue
under the skin, mucous
membranes. They begin as
blind-ended tubes in
these microcapillary beds.
Lymphatic capillaries
converge in large lymphatic
vessels, eventually
unite and form two main
channels that empty to the
vascular system by draining
into the large veins and
the base of the neck.
Lymph enters the blood
at the junction of
the internal jugular
and subclavian veins.
The largest lymphatic
vessel, the thoracic
duct, drains most of
the body, but the rest
of the body, the right
upper quartile quadrant,
is drained by the
right lymphatic duct.
There's greater
permeability than blood
capillaries, so they're
much more effective in
removing intracellular
proteins and fluid.
Once the lymph, once
this tissue fluid enters
the lymphatic vessel,
it is known as lymph.
So, the lymphatics also
transport proteins, lipids
that are too large to cross
the fenestration of the
absorption capillaries and
the small intestine. So,
lymphatics are important
in the small intestine too.
So before the lymph returns
to the blood, it passes
through the lymph nose
where it's exposed to cells
of the lymphatic system
and tends to pick up white
blood cells as the lymph
passes through these nodes.
There's no central pump in
the lymphatic system. They
do have unidirectional
valves, so what's important in
projecting forward flow of
lymphatics are compression
of skeletal muscles,
for instance. This is an
area, lymphatic flow, that
there are OMM procedures
that I think may turn out
to be very, very positive
because there's evidence
that that sluggish
lymphatic flow does not
adequately remove the toxins
in your body and some of
these OMM procedures I
think are going to be shown
to help in that process.
So the lymphatics you
have, here's a lymphatic
capillary here and they
have some kind of unique
structures. They tend to
be collapse for the most
part, but when you have
a lot of tissue fluid
buildup, that actually
expands because of these
anchoring filaments, that
actually causes these
vessels to become more
dilated, and then fluid can
flow into these gaps in
between the endothelium.
so endothelial the endothelium
lining these lymphatics
they do not have a continuous
basal lamina so the
lymphatic vessels become thicker
as the walls develop more
connective tissue and smooth
muscle tissue as you move
towards the heart and they
become larger and larger
so here's an example
of a lymphatic
duct this could be thoracic
or the right lymphatic duct
so these larger lymphatic
vessels do have some smooth
muscle you can see smooth
muscle here but there it's
difficult to distinguish
the boundaries and of course
in some of the veins that's
a little bit more difficult
than the arteries but it
becomes even more difficult
to distinguish the layers
of these lymphatics. So
basically you have an
endothelial inner layer and you
might have what could
potentially be called a tunica
media and then an adventitia,
but these layers are not
very prominent and easily
discernible, particularly
as you get into smaller and
smaller lymphatic vessels.
So here is a larger
lymphatic vessel
and you can see it
has a large lumen.
You can see some smooth
muscle associated with
but not continuous with
this lymphatic vessel.
Lymphatic capillaries, here's
an example of a lymphatic
capillary. You can see
it has only white blood
cells in the lumen, which
kind of gives it away. Here
you can see an associated
arteriole over here, but
this is a lymphatic, a
small lymphatic capillary.
Again, if it were filled
with red blood cells, you
would know that this was
probably a small venule
instead of a lymphatic
capillary so here again you
can see thoracic duct is
a pretty thick wall it's
a one of the larger
lymphatic vessels but they're
primarily could collapse
as you notice in gross
anatomy lab again the layering
is indistinct but there
are some smooth muscle
cells the key thing that
you will see in the lumen
of a thoracic duct, if you
look at it histologically,
you might see white
blood cells, but you would
not see red blood cells.
Now, this is an example
of a lymphatic vessel,
and you can see the
valve here. You see some
lymphocytes inside this.
This material here is
not red blood cells,
it's a coagulated lymph.
Over here, you can
see what looks like
another vessel. It has
white blood cells here,
so I would not want to
identify that right now,
but it looks a little
bit more like a venule.
But because you don't
see any red blood cells,
it's probably another
branch of lymphatic.
Again, you can't really
identify everything
in these sections, but
the main feature is
to remember you should
be able to identify.
So, again, here you
have a really good
example of those
different layers of an
artery and a vein and
a lymphatic up here.
Again, this has red
blood cells in it.
This has red blood
cells in it. Red
blood cells in it.
So, clearly a venule.
This looks like it could
be a lymph vessel here.
and again this just summarizes
all the things that you
should know again use the
classroom study guide to
look at these these specific
aims and that's where the
test questions come from
and you can also zoom into
that slide that I talked
about earlier of the heart
from University of Michigan
site but this is also a
really good slide for you
this is also a very good site
for you to zoom in and
zoom out as if you had a
microscope and identify different
blood vessels I'll leave
you with this far side
cartoon one of my favorites
pull out Betty pull out you
hit an artery so you see
the mosquito it's like
obviously under high pressure
Thank you.